let A and B be two positive real numbers
and consider an a by B rectangle that
has area a times B
now create four copies of this rectangle
in closing an area of four times a times
B
these four rectangles can be organized
to fit inside of an A plus b by a plus b
square however there's a missing
interior square with a side length of B
minus a
from this diagram we see that the
quantity a plus b squared minus the
quantity B minus a squared must be equal
to the quantity four times a times B
if we remove the inner Square we see
that the quantity a plus b squared is
greater than or equal to 4 times a times
B this is true for all positive Pairs
and we see that we get equality between
a plus b squared and 4 a b if and only
if a equals B taking square roots and
dividing by 2 yields the arithmetic mean
geometric mean inequality